<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ordinary Differential Equation | Aprende con Alf</title><link>/en/tag/ordinary-differential-equation/</link><atom:link href="/en/tag/ordinary-differential-equation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Ordinary Differential Equation</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><image><url>/images/logo_hude38443eeb2faa5fa84365aba7d86a77_3514_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url><title>Ordinary Differential Equation</title><link>/en/tag/ordinary-differential-equation/</link></image><item><title>Ordinary differential equations</title><link>/en/teaching/calculus/manual/ordinary-differential-equations/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/teaching/calculus/manual/ordinary-differential-equations/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="ordinary-differential-equations">Ordinary Differential Equations&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Often in Physics, Chemistry, Biology, Geometry, etc there arise equations that relate a function with its derivative, or successive derivatives.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="alert alert-def">
&lt;div>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Definition - Ordinary differential equation&lt;/strong>. An &lt;em>ordinary differential equation&lt;/em> (O.D.E.) is a equation that relates an independent variable $x$, a function $y(x)$ that depends on $x$, and the successive derivatives of $y$, $y&amp;rsquo;,y&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;,\ldots,y^{(n)}$; it can be written as&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$F(x, y, y&amp;rsquo;, y&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;,\ldots, y^{(n)})=0.$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The &lt;em>order&lt;/em> of a differential equation is the greatest order of the derivatives in the equation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Example&lt;/strong>. The equation $y&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;+sen(x)y&amp;rsquo;=2x$ is a differential equation of order 3.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="deducing-a-differential-equation">Deducing a differential equation&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>To deduce a differential equation that explains a natural phenomenon is essential to understand what a derivative is and how to interpret it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Example&lt;/strong>. Newton’s law of cooling states&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;em>“The rate of change of the temperature of a body in a surrounding medium is proportional to the difference between the temperature of the body $T$ and the temperature of the medium $T_a$.”&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The rate of change of the temperature is the derivative of temperature with respect to time $dT/dt$. Thus, Newton’s law of cooling can be explained by the differential equation&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\frac{dT}{dt}=k(T-T_a),$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>where $k$ is a proportionality constant.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="solution-of-an-ordinary-differential-equation">Solution of an ordinary differential equation&lt;/h3>
&lt;div class="alert alert-def">
&lt;div>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Definition - Solution of an ordinary differential equation&lt;/strong>. Given an ordinary differential equation $F(x,y,y&amp;rsquo;,y&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;,\ldots,y^{(n})=0$, the function $y=f(x)$ is a &lt;em>solution of the ordinary differential equation&lt;/em> if it satisfies the equation, that is, if&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$F(x,f(x), f&amp;rsquo;(x), f&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;(x),\ldots, f^{(n}(x))=0.$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The graph of a solution of the ordinary differential equation is known as &lt;em>integral curve&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Solving an ordinary differential equations consists on finding all its solutions in a given domain. For that integral calculus is required.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The same manner than the indefinite integral is a family of antiderivatives, that differ in a constant term, after integrating an ordinary differential equation we get a family of solutions that differ in a constant. We can get particular solutions giving values to this constant.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="general-solution-of-an-ordinary-differential-equation">General solution of an ordinary differential equation&lt;/h3>
&lt;div class="alert alert-def">
&lt;div>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Definition - General solution of an ordinary differential equation&lt;/strong>. Given an ordinary differential equation $F(x,y,y&amp;rsquo;,y&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;,\ldots,y^{(n})=0$ of order $n$, the &lt;em>general solution&lt;/em> of the differential equation is a family of functions&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$y =f (x,C_1,\ldots,C_n),$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>depending on $n$ constants, such that for any value of $C_1,\ldots,C_n$ we get a solution of the differential equation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>For every value of the constant we get &lt;em>particular solution&lt;/em> of the differential equation. Thus, when a differential equation can be solved, it has infinite solutions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Geometrically, the general solution of a differential equation corresponds to a family of integral curves of the differential equation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Often, it is common to impose conditions to the solutions of a differential equation to reduce the number of solutions. In many cases, these conditions allow to determine the values of the constants in the general solution to get a particular solution.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="first-order-differential-equations">First order differential equations&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In this chapter we are going to study first order differential equations&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$F(x,y,y&amp;rsquo;)=0.$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The general solution of a first order differential equation is&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$y = f (x,C),$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>so to get a particular solution from the general one, it is enough to set the value of the constant $C$, and for that we only need to impose one initial condition.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="alert alert-def">
&lt;div>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Definition - Initial value problem&lt;/strong>. The group consisting of a first order differential equation and an initial condition is known as &lt;em>initial value problem&lt;/em>:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$
\begin{cases}
F(x,y,y&amp;rsquo;)=0, &amp;amp; \mbox{First order differential equation;} \newline
y(x_0)=y_0, &amp;amp; \mbox{Initial condition.}
\end{cases}
$$&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Solving an initial value problem consists in finding a solution of the first order differential equation that satisfies the initial condition.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Example&lt;/strong>. Recall the first order differential equation of the Newton’s law of cooling, $$\frac{dT}{dt}=k(T-T_a),$$
where $T$ is the temperature of the body and $T_a$ is the temperature of the surrounding medium.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It is easy to check that the general solution of this equation is&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$T(t) = Ce^{kt}+T_a.$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If we impose the initial condition that the temperature of the body at the initial instant is $5$ ºC, that is, $T(0)=5$, we have&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$T(0) = Ce^{k\cdot0}+T_a = C+T_a = 5,$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>from where we get $C=5-T_a$, and this give us the particular solution&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$T(t) = (5-T_a)e^{kt}+T_a.$$&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="integral-curve-of-an-initial-value-problem">Integral curve of an initial value problem&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Example&lt;/strong>. If we assume in the previous example that the temperature of the surrounding medium is $T_a=0$ ºC and the cooling constant of the body is $k=1$, the general solution of the differential equation is
$$T(t)=Ce^t,$$
that is a family of integral curves. Among all of them, only the one that passes through the point $(0,5)$ corresponds to the particular solution of the previous initial value problem.&lt;/p>
&lt;img src="../img/ode/integral_curves.svg" alt="Area of a positive function" width="350">
&lt;h3 id="existence-and-uniqueness-of-solutions">Existence and uniqueness of solutions&lt;/h3>
&lt;div class="alert alert-theo">
&lt;div>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Theorem - Existence and uniqueness of solutions of a first order ODE&lt;/strong>. Given an initial value problem&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\begin{cases}
y&amp;rsquo;=F(x,y);\newline
y(x_0)=y_0;
\end{cases}
$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>if $F(x,y(x))$ is a function continuous on an open interval around the point $(x_0,y_0)$, then a solution of the initial value problem exists. If, in addition, $\frac{\partial F}{\partial y}$ is continuous in an open interval around $(x_0,y_0)$, the solution is unique.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Although this theorem guarantees the existence and uniqueness of a solution of a first order differential equation, it does not provide a method to compute it. In fact, there is not a general method to solve first order differential equations, but we will see how to solve some types:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="#separable-differential-equations">Separable differential equations&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="#homogeneous-differential-equations">Homogeneous differential equations&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="#linear-differential-equations">Linear differential equations&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="separable-differential-equations">Separable differential equations&lt;/h2>
&lt;div class="alert alert-def">
&lt;div>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Definition - Separable differential equation&lt;/strong>. A &lt;em>separable differential equation&lt;/em> is a first order differential equation that can be written as&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$y&amp;rsquo;g(y)=f(x),$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>or what is the same,&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$g(y)dy=f(x)dx,$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>so the different variables are on different sides of the equality (the variables are separated).&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="alert alert-tool">
&lt;div>
&lt;p>The general solution for a separable differential equation comes after integrating both sides of the equation&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\int g(y)\,dy = \int f(x)\,dx+C.$$&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Example&lt;/strong>. The differential equation of the Newton’s law of cooling&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\frac{dT}{dt}=k(T-T_a),$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>is a separable differential equation since it can be written as&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\frac{1}{T-T_a}dT=k\,dt.$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Integrating both sides of the equation we have&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\int \frac{1}{T-T_a}\,dT=\int k\,dt\Leftrightarrow \log(T-T_a)=kt+C,$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>and solving for $T$ we get the general solution of the equation&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$T(t)=e^{kt+C}+T_a=e^Ce^{kt}+T_a=Ce^{kt}+T_a,$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>rewriting $C=e^C$ as an arbitrary constant.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="homogeneous-differential-equations">Homogeneous differential equations&lt;/h2>
&lt;div class="alert alert-def">
&lt;div>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Definition - Homogeneous function&lt;/strong>. A function $f(x,y)$ is &lt;em>homogeneous&lt;/em> of degree $n$, if it satisfies&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$f(kx,ky)= k^nf(x,y),$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>for any value $k\in \mathbb{R}$.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>In particular, a homogeneous function of degree $0$ always satisfies&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$f(kx,ky)=f(x,y).$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Setting $k=1/x$ we have&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$f(x,y)=f\left(\frac{1}{x}x,\frac{1}{x}y\right)=f\left(1,\frac{y}{x}\right)=g\left(\frac{y}{x}\right).$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This way, a homogeneous function of degree $0$ always can be written as a function of $u=y/x$:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$f(x,y)=g\left(\frac{y}{x}\right)=g(u).$$&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="alert alert-def">
&lt;div>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Definition - Homogeneous differential equation&lt;/strong>. A &lt;em>homogeneous differential equation&lt;/em> is a first order differential equation that can be written as&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$y&amp;rsquo;=f(x,y),$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>where $f(x,y)$ is a homogeneous function of degree $0$.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="alert alert-tool">
&lt;div>
&lt;p>We can solve a homogeneous differential equation by making the substitution&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$u=\frac{y}{x}\Leftrightarrow y=ux,$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>so the equation becomes&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$u&amp;rsquo;x+u=f(u),$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>that is a separable differential equation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Once solved the separable differential equation, the substitution must be undone.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Example&lt;/strong>. Let us consider the following differential equation
$$4x-3y+y&amp;rsquo;(2y-3x)=0.$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rewriting the equation in this way&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$y&amp;rsquo;=\frac{3y-4x}{2y-3x}$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>we can easily check that it is a homogeneous differential equation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To solve this equation we have to do the substitution $y=ux$, and we get&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$u&amp;rsquo;x+u=\frac{3ux-4x}{2ux-3x}=\frac{3u-4}{2u-3}$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>that is a separable differential equation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Separating the variables we have&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$u&amp;rsquo;x=\frac{3u-4}{2u-3}-u=\frac{-2u^2+6u-4}{2u-3}\Leftrightarrow \frac{2u-3}{-2u^2+6u-4}\,du=\frac{1}{x}\,dx.$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now, integrating both sides of the equation we have&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$
\renewcommand{\arraystretch}{2}
\begin{array}{c}
\displaystyle \int \frac{2u-3}{-2u^2+6u-4}\,du=\int \frac{1}{x}\,dx
\Leftrightarrow -\frac{1}{2}\log|u^2-3u+2|=\log|x|+C \Leftrightarrow\newline
\Leftrightarrow \log|u^2-3u+2|=-2\log|x|-2C,
\end{array}
$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>then, applying the exponential function to both sides and simplifying we get the general solution&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$u^2-3u+2=e^{-2\log|x|-2C}=\frac{e^{-2C}}{e^{\log|x|^2}}=\frac{C}{x^2},$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>rewriting the constant $K=e^{-2C}$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finally, undoing the initial substitution $u=y/x$, we arrive at the general solution of the homogeneous differential equation&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\left(\frac{y}{x}\right)^2-3\frac{y}{x}+2=\frac{K}{x^2}\Leftrightarrow y^2-3xy+2x^2=K.$$&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="linear-differential-equations">Linear differential equations&lt;/h3>
&lt;div class="alert alert-def">
&lt;div>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Definition - Linear differential equation&lt;/strong> A &lt;em>linear differential equation&lt;/em> is a first order differential equation that can be written as&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$y&amp;rsquo;+g(x)y = h(x).$$&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>To solve a linear differential equation we try to write the left side of the equation as the derivative of a product. For that we multiply both sides by the function $f(x)$, such that&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$f&amp;rsquo;(x)=g(x)f(x).$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thus, we get&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$
\begin{array}{c}
y&amp;rsquo;f(x)+g(x)f(x)y=h(x)f(x)\newline
\Updownarrow\newline
y&amp;rsquo;f(x)+f&amp;rsquo;(x)y=h(x)f(x)\newline
\Updownarrow\newline
\dfrac{d}{dx}(yf(x))=h(x)f(x)
\end{array}
$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Integrating both sides of the previous equation we get the solution&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$yf(x)=\int h(x)f(x)\,dx+C.$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On the other hand, the unique function that satisfies $f&amp;rsquo;(x)=g(x)f(x)$ is&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$f(x)=e^{\int g(x)\,dx},$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>so, substituting this function in the previous solution we arrive at the solution of the linear differential equation&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$ye^{\int g(x)\,dx}=\int h(x) e^{\int g(x)\,dx}\,dx+C,$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>or what is the same&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="alert alert-tool">
&lt;div>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Solution of a linear differential equation&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$y=e^{-\int g(x)\,dx}\left(\int h(x)e^{\int g(x)\,dx}\,dx+C\right).$$&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Example&lt;/strong>. If in the differential equation of the Newton’s law of cooling the temperature of the surrounding medium is a function of time $T_a(t)$, then the differential equation&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\frac{dT}{dt}=k(T-T_a(t)),$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>is a linear differential equation since it can be written as&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$T&amp;rsquo;-kT=-kT_a(t),$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>where the independent term is $-kT_a(t)$ and the coefficient of $T$ is $-k$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Substituting in the formula of the general solution of a linear differential equation we have&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$y=e^{-\int -k\,dt}\left(\int -kT_a(t)e^{\int -k\,dt}\,dt+C\right)=
e^{kt}\left(-\int kT_a(t)e^{-kt}\,dt+C\right).$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the particular case that $T_a(t)=t$, and the proportionality constant $k=1$, the general solution of the linear differential equation is&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$y=e^{t}\left(-\int te^{-kt}\,dt+C\right)=e^t(e^{-t}(t+1)+C)=Ce^t+t+1.$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If, in addition, we know that the temperature of the body at time $t=0$ is $5$ ºC, that is, we have the initial condition $T(0)=5$, then we can compute the value of the constant $C$,&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$y(0)=Ce^0+0+1=5 \Leftrightarrow C+1=5 \Leftrightarrow C=4,$$
and we get the particular solution&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$y(t)=4e^t+t+1.$$&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>